Guide to the Fabrique Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Fabrique family papers
1771-1897
MS 201
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(2 boxes)
Records of the Fabrique family on their emigration from Languedoc, France to Newtown, Conn. Included are account books, diaries, military records, genealogies and architectural plans for meeting houses at Southbury, Roxbury and Oxford, Conn. Also the papers of Charles Fabrique (1817-1889) containing his correspondence while at Yale College, diaries and account books.
Fabrique family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
CHARLES FABRIQUE, 1817-1889
CHARLES FABRIQUE (Oxford, Conn.), eldest son of William L. and Hannah (Johnson) Fabrique, was born in Southbury, Conn., April 10, 1817. His parents removed to the adjoining town of Oxford in his infancy, where his boyhood was chiefly passed on a farm and in the district school, and where he remained until 1836, when he commenced fitting for college in the "Kimball Union Academy," at Meriden, N. H., remaining there until he entered college in August 1838.
After graduation, he spent two years and a half in the Theological Department of Yale College, taking advantage, at the same time, of the lectures in the Law and Medical Schools, connected with the same institution. In April 1845, he was invited to take charge of the academy (now high school) in Waterbury, Conn., and officiated as principal of that school until August 1852, acquiring in the mean time a high reputation as a teacher. After resigning his educational charge in Waterbury, he spent several months in traveling and in such other recreation as a temporary relief from his labors permitted him to enjoy.
In April 1853, he removed to New Haven, Conn., where he resumed the profession of teacher and spent twenty years in preparing boys for college and fitting them for business life, in a boarding and day school in that city. In his long and arduous labors in this special department of instruction, it is due to Mr. Fabrique to say, that he was eminently successful as a teacher, securing in the highest degree the public confidence, and most happily uniting the best qualities of the disciplinarian with those of the able instructor.
During his residence in New Haven, Mr. Fabrique has filled several important public positions, having served in both branches of the Common Council-three years as councilman and one year as alderman-and been a much longer time on the Board of Police Commissioners. He also took a very active and efficient part in organizing the Industrial School for girls, now located at Middletown, having been the first to petition the Legislature of the State for the establishment of that institution, and, at one time, laboring almost single handed and alone to advance that important and now thoroughly successful enterprise.
Since September 1873, he has been conducting the affairs of the New Haven Brush Company, whose manufacturing establishment is situated at the outlet of Saltonstall Lake in East Haven, having a valuable water power and prospectively a fine business.
He was married, July 14, 1845, to Miss Caroline S. Eastman, of New Haven, Conn., by whom he has had two children, both sons, the first born September 22, 1857, and the second, born February 26, 1861; died August 25, 1862.
Scope and Contents
Records of the Fabrique family on their emigration from Languedoc, France to Newtown, Conn. Included are account books, diaries, military records, genealogies and architectural plans for meeting houses at Southbury, Roxbury and Oxford, Conn. Also the papers of Charles Fabrique (1817-1889) containing his correspondence while at Yale College, diaries and account books.
Education; Families; French -- United States; Connecticut; Oxford (Conn.); Roxbury (Conn.: Town); Southbury (Conn.); Account books; Diaries; Fabrique, Charles, 1817-1889; Fabrique family; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  - Architectural plans for the Southbury, Ct. meetinghouse, the Roxbury, Ct. meetinghouse, the Oxford, Ct. meetinghouse, and several private dwellings, 1771, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Account book showing sales of wood, farm produce, and related services, with genealogical notes on the family of John Fabrique of Languedoc, France, and Newtown, Ct., and a booklet, containing an alphabetical list of persons' names followed by numbers, 1785-1824, undated (Box 2)
  - List of pupils, attendance, and tuition payments at a school in Oxford, Ct., with William L. Fabrique among the students, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Annual Inspection Return of the 2nd Company of the 13th Regiment of Connecticut Militia," listing men (including William L. Fabrique) and equipment, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Eunice (J[ohnson?]) Eastman Bradley) Mrs. Richard Eastman, Mrs. Monson Bradley): diary, 1816-1863 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Charles Fabrique (1817-1889) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with William L. and Hannah (Johnson) Fabrique, 1836-1842, undated
    - Bill and list of graduates from Yale College, 1839, undated
    - Letter from L. M. Browne relating to a theatrical production in Oxford, Ct., undated
    - Unidentified photograph of a young man, undated
    - Diary and memorandum book, 1836-1837 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Personal account book, 1846-1852
    - Personal account and memorandum book, 1867-1868
    - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers
      General note
      See: Folder 12 and 13
  - Waterbury, Ct., public schools: committee reports, 1838, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - F. W. B.: letters to the Sabbath School Scholars in Oxford, 1841, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers, 1786-1793 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers, 1813-1837 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers, 1845-1855 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous legal and financial papers, 1863-1893, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous letters, 1816-1897, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Genealogical notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)